Guide to the Angus MacLise Sound Recordings
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Angus MacLise sound recordings
1965-1978
YCAL MSS 445
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
2
(2 boxes)
The Angus MacLise Sound Recordings document selected musical work of Angus MacLise. The sound recordings are 5 and 7.5 inch reel-to-reel audio tapes that consist of experimental music composed and performed by MacLise in solo performances and in collaboration with other musicians and artists. The recordings span the years 1965 to 1978.
MacLise, Angus
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Hetty MacLise, July 2008.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Boxes 1-2 (audiovisual material): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Angus MacLise
Angus MacLise was born on March 4, 1938 in Bridgeport, CT. He studied various genres of percussion and dance, performing with several ensembles before entering the downtown New York City music scene. In the early 1960s, he wrote and published poetry through Dead Language Press, which he co-founded with filmmaker Piero Heliczer. The press also published MacLise's combination calendar/poem, Year, which assigned names to each day of the year. MacLise was a member of La Monte Young's Theater of Eternal Music with John Cale, Tony Conrad, Marian Zazeela, and Terry Riley. In 1965, MacLise lived with Cale and along with him, Lou Reed and Sterling Morrison, formed the musical group The Velvet Underground. MacLise performed with them regularly throughout the year but quit in late 1965 and was replaced by Maureen Tucker. He played with them again for a few performances in 1966 when Reed was briefly hospitalized.
McLise was a student of the occultist and mystic Aleister Crowley and under the influence of his teachings, began to blend Tibetan mysticism with his music to create sound through various drone techniques. From 1965 through the 1970s, MacLise was active in the New York City underground music scene, integrating trance, improvisation, spoken word, poetry, and electronics into his performances. He collaborated with several notable artists on multimedia projects, such as Gerard Malanga, Yoko Ono, Jonas Mekas, and Jerry Jofen. In the late 1960s, MacLise married illustrator Hetty McGee, and together they played in the musical group, Universal Mutant Repertory Company. The group did a series of performances in New York's St. Mark's Church in 1970, titled "Epiphanies." In the early 1970s, he devoted more of his time to poetry and calligraphy, and also started a literary magazine, Ting-Pa.
Later in his life, MacLise traveled to study the ethnic percussion traditions in Morocco, Turkey, Syria, Iraq, Iran, Afghanistan, Pakistan, and India with various local teachers and groups. He settled in Nepal, where he died of hypoglycemia in Kathmandu on June 21, 1979.
Scope and Contents
The Angus MacLise Sound Recordings document the musical work of Angus MacLise. The reel-to-reel audio tapes consist of experimental music performed by MacLise in solo performances and in collaboration with other musicians and artists. The sound recordings span the years 1965 to 1978.
Arrangement
Arranged according to a numbering system assigned by MacLise.
Musicians -- 20th Century; American poetry -- 20th Century; Avante-garde (Music) -- United States -- 20th Century; Songs with instrumental ensemble; Songs with percussion; Audiovisual materials; Sound recordings; MacLise, Angus
- Sound Recordings, 1965-1978; 2; (2 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Sound recordings are arranged according to a numbering system assigned by MacLise, "GM/AM 001-025." "GM" stands for Gerard Malanga, who assisted Hetty MacLise in rehousing the tapes before their transfer to the Beinecke Library. "AM" stands for Angus MacLise.
  Scope and Contents
  The sound recordings consist of 28 reel-to-reel audio tapes. Most tapes have been rehoused into new reel boxes by Hetty MacLise and Malanga. Original boxes are filed next to the rehoused tapes since the original boxes contain MacLise's notes. Titles have been transcribed from original boxes. Tapes 1-9, and 24 are 7.5 inch reels. Tapes 10-23 and 25 are 5 inch reels.
  There are three numbered tapes at the end of the series that are in original boxes. These tapes include GM/AM numbers that do not correspond to rehoused tapes. All are 7.5 inch reels. It is not clear as to why they were assigned duplicate numbers but were not rehoused. It is possible that they were not reviewed by Hetty MacLise and Malanga.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Boxes 1 and 2 (audiovisual material): Restricted fragile. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
  - GM/AM-001. "Untitled. 7.5 ips, 2-track stereo.", 1964 December 23; 1; 01:46:16; The first hour and 22 minutes is recorded at a very low level at times. The audio speeds up at times in the first four minutes. Stops and starts can also be heard. Static is heard on the tape. The program is distorted at times. (Box 1, Folder 1, Item barcode 39002104616082)
    Audiovisual material. Restricted fragile. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
  - GM/AM-002. "Recorded on Tandberg tape recorder. Epiphany at St. Mark's Church in the Bowery. 1970 January 6. 7.5 ips.", 1; 01:35:04; The program begins and ends abruptly. The audio cuts in and out throughout the first 47 and a half minutes. The program is distorted at times. The program is recorded at a very high level. Audio in the right channel cuts out from around 1:12:26-1:18:59. (Box 1, Folder 2, Item barcode 39002104616090)
  - GM/AM-003. "Musicians: Angus MacLise, Bill Breeze, Mark Slivka. Note: one track appears to come through from a second track. 3.75 ips half track one side. Other side 7.5 ips half track David Lewiston's Central Park tapes-1970.", 1970, 1978; 1; 01:06:49; The program ends abruptly. The program is distorted at times. (Box 1, Folder 3, Item barcode 39002104616108)
  - GM/AM-004. "Side 1: Expanded Media. Track A-Tibetan (Sikhim) chant and gong, 2/3 of tape. Track B- Electronic RTF experimental, last few minutes Tibetan again. 7.5 ips.", 1965 November 16; 1; 01:21:20; Static can be heard on the tape. The program is distorted at times. Buzz can be heard on the tape from 23:45-47:07. A slight warble on the tape can be heard at about 1:17:00. (Box 1, Folder 4, Item barcode 39002104616116)
  - GM/AM-005. "Quasar, St. Mark's in the Bowery. Note: Angus and Don's collaboration for Don's St. Mark's show. Performers: J. Taylor-organ, Frank-drums (Rabuffo's husband), Barney Rosteing-sax, Jimmy Lovelace-trumpet. 7.5 ips.", 1967 December; 1; 00:31:15; Speed flucutations can be heard at about five seconds into the program. (Box 1, Folder 5, Item barcode 39002104616124)
  - GM/AM-006. "Fantuzzi- India departure and MacLise Energy Center party. 7.5 ips mono full track. 32 minutes recording time.", 1976 November 20; 1; 00:32:33; The program is distorted at times. It is recorded at a very high level. The program begins and ends abruptly. (Box 1, Folder 6, Item barcode 39002104616132)
  - GM/AM-007. "Master- includes teachings. Alternate readings with prepared piano/flute/percussion. Players not listed. Angus MacLise 1st meeting with Tim Leary?", circa 1965; 1; 01:00:03; A high amount of hiss can be heard on the tape. The program is distorted at times. Static can be heard. The program ends abruptly. (Box 1, Folder 7, Item barcode 39002104616140)
  - GM/AM-008. "The Destruction and Rebirth of the Planet Earth. Marymount Ritual.", 1969 May; 1; 01:19:35; The program is distorted at times. The program is in silence from about 1:07:12-1:11:43. (Box 1, Folder 8, Item barcode 39002104616157)
  - GM/AM-009. "Dracula (synthesizer), 7.5 ips half track. Approximately 12 minutes recording time.", 1978 March; 1; 00:17:30; Static can be heard on the tape. (Box 1, Folder 9, Item barcode 39002104616165)
  - GM/AM-010. "Untitled tracks plus Central Park. Binding: left session with Bill Breeze, Hilary Harris, Angus MacLise. 7.5 ips, ½ track stereo.", [1970], 1978; 1; 00:45:03; The program begins and ends abruptly. The program is distorted at times. (Box 1, Folder 10, Item barcode 39002104616173)
  - GM/AM-011. "Epiphany and Three Magi. Angus MacLise-tabla, Ira Cohen-chimes and bells, Hetty MacLise-flute, organ and voice, Lauren Standlee- guitar. Approximately 23 minutes playing time. 7.5 ips.", undated; 1; 00:47:38; The program is distorted at times. Static can be heard. (Box 1, Folder 11, Item barcode 39002104616181)
  - GM/AM-012. "Orion de Winter. Beelzebub-Frisco Jam session. 3.75 ips, 1side, approximately 32 minutes.", undated; 1; 00:31:16; The program is distorted at times. A warble in the audio can be heard throughout the program. (Box 1, Folder 12, Item barcode 39002104616199)
  - GM/AM-013. "Goeralegan session 1. 3.75 ips, poor sound quality"., circa 1969; 1; 00:19:55; The program ends abruptly. (Box 1, Folder 13, Item barcode 39002104616207)
  - GM/AM-014. "Goeralegan and Dedication Ceremony of Mount Shango, sessions 1 and 2. Steve Elliott, Bill Spesard, Carl Kosoff, Kit Lascoutx, Michael McClanathan, Consuela, Rene, and Angus MacLise. 3.75 ips full track Nagra, approximately 30 minutes.", circa 1969; 1; 00:30:05; The program begins and ends abruptly. (Box 1, Folder 14, Item barcode 39002104616215)
  - GM/AM-015. "Goeralegan and Hetty's Birth Rituals. Plus Part 1- Dedication of Mount Shango. Benne Friedman, Jim Jacobs, Jerry Martin, Irene Noland and some voices in background. 3.75 ips full track.", 1969; 1; 00:48:34; A warble in the audio is heard at the end of the tape. (Box 1, Folder 15, Item barcode 39002104616223)
  - GM/AM-016. "First Session. Benne Friedman-guitar, Ben Shawinsky-bamboo flute, Angus MacLise-Amerindian logdrum. 7.5 ips, dual track.", 1978 May 5; 1 (Box 1, Folder 16, Item barcode 39002104616231)
  - GM/AM-017. "Side 1: Epiphany-St. Mark's Church. Rehearsal. 7.5 ips. Side 2: 3.75 ips. Approximately 1 hour, 37 minutes.", 1970 January 6; 1 (Box 2, Folder 17, Item barcode 39002104616249)
  - GM/AM-018. "Berkshire MacLisinites (Everybody). 3.75 and 7.5 ips .", circa1969; 1 (Box 2, Folder 18, Item barcode 39002104616256)
  - GM/AM-019 a & b. "a) Birth and Death of the Planet Earth. Marymount show, live. Rehearsal, track 1. b) Drums and live show, track 2. 3.75 ips. Approximately 63 minutes.", 1970; 1 (Box 2, Folder 19, Item barcode 39002104616264)
  - GM/AM-020. "Untitled. Participants: Ben Shawinksy-flute and whistle glass, Don Snyder-harmonica, Jim Jacobs-window flute, Angus MacLise-director/recorder. 7.5 ips, approximately 22 minutes.", circa 1969; 1 (Box 2, Folder 20, Item barcode 39002104616272)
  - GM/AM-021. "Goeralegan 2 and Hetty's Birth Ritual. Participants: Angus MacLise-cello and tabla, Hetty MacLise and Don Snyder-cello, 3.75 ips, approximately 23 minutes of a 48 minutes recording existing.", 1969; 1 (Box 2, Folder 21, Item barcode 39002104616280)
  - GM/AM-022. "Untitled. Overdub of Angus MacLise on drums. Unidentified: Jew's Harp. Angus on flute plus 'Dr. Shelley.' 3.75 ips, full track, approximately 49 minutes.", undated; 1 (Box 2, Folder 22, Item barcode 39002104616298)
  - GM/AM-023. "Tribal Group and Angus's Angels. Participants: Ben Shawinsky, Jerry Martin, Jim Jacobs, Don Snyder, Charles Mingus Jr., Sherri, Mikki Snyder, Deegan Snyder, Benne Friedman. 7.5 ips, approximately 43 minutes.", 1970; 1 (Box 2, Folder 23, Item barcode 39002104616306)
  - GM/AM-024. "Track 1, Side 1: Forest and Aztec Chant. Track 2, Side 2: Drums and insect voices backwards. 7.5 ips with a 3.75 ips, 5 minute changeover. Note: Track 1, Side 2 and Track 2, Side 1 could not be located on tape. Approximately 30 minutes.", circa 1970; 1 (Box 2, Folder 24, Item barcode 39002104616314)
  - GM/AM-025. "Fantuzzi Blow-out. Energy Center, departure for India music party. 3.75 ips with 7.5 changeovers. Mono approximately 63 minutes.", 1976; 1 (Box 2, Folder 25, Item barcode 39002104616322)
  - GM/AM-005. "Goeralegan and Dedication Ceremony (christening) of Mount Shango. Drums, flute declamation. Opens with Mick Jagger.", 1968; 1 (Box 2, Folder 26, Item barcode 39002104616330)
  - GM/AM-007. "Epiphany stereo 7.5, recording on side 1 only, Hetty chant and organ.", undated; 1 (Box 2, Folder 27, Item barcode 39002104616348)
  - GM/AM-010. "Party, master track 1, 2, 3. Mostly blank.", 1971 October 16; 1 (Box 2, Folder 28, Item barcode 39002104616355)